Guide to the Robert Compton Papers
The Wittliff Collections
- Correspondence, 1955-2008
  - Sanders, Leonard, 1980-1984 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Sanford, Annette, 1989-1998 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Scharnhorst, Gary [University of New Mexico], 1981-1993 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Schlossstein, Steven B., 1982-1984 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Schulte, Rainer, 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Schutze, Jim, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Scofield, Sandra, 1993-1997 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Seligmann, Jr., Gus [North Texas State University], 1980 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Shearer, Bill, 1982-1996 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    Correspondence about books written (author), publishing books
  - Sherrill, Robert, 1980-1994 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Shuler, Linda Lay, 1987-1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Slate, Audry [University of Texas at Austin], 1983 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Smith, C.W., 1985-1991 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Smith, Henry Nash, 1981-1989 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Spann, Philip C., 1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Staines, David, 1981-1987 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Stowers, Carlton, 1970-1996 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Stratton, W.K. (Kip), 1990-1999 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Swift, Edward, 1982-1990 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Swindell, Larry [Dallas Morning News], 1998 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Correspondence about newspaper (editor, journalist), newspaper clipping, Pulitzer Prize winner
  - T - Z, 1979-1996 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Tasma, Jean Marie; Taylor, Sheila; Teague, William J.; Thompson, Lou Ann; Thompson, Thomas H.; Trickett; David G.; Turrentine, Jeff; Tynes, Teresa; Vawrinek, Jeffrey J.; Waldron, Ann; Warner, Sharon Oard; Watkins, Kay; West, Richard; Wheeler, John A.; Williams, Rittal; Wilson, Laura; Wolfe, Jane; Young, Mark W.; Yarbrough, David; Yemma, Mark; Zagst, Michael; Correspondence about book reviews, thank you letters, Author requests, photograph, copies of newspaper articles
  - Taylor, Henry, 1979-1986 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    Correspondence about bookstore
  - Taylor, Marshall [Southern Methodist University], 1980-1988 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Tinkle, Lon, 1979-1993 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    Correspondence about books written (author), pencil drawing
  - Trammell, Robert and Gerald Burns, 1985-1987 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Tucker, Chris, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Vick, Fran, 1981-2008 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Correspondence about books written (author), publishing, newspaper clipping
  - Vliet, Ann and R.G., 1985-1991 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Correspondence about book reviews, books written (author), three photographs
  - Voigt, Elsie, 1986-1989 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Wagner, Sherry, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Walker, Dale, 1986-1990 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Wardlaw, Frank [Texas A&M Press], 1974-1986 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Correspondence about publishing, photograph, newspaper clipping
  - Watt, Donley [Trinity University], 1988-2001 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Weber, David [Southern Methodist University], 1980-1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Weems, Ed, 1980-1999 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Correspondence about book reviews, books written (author), photographs, newspaper clippings
  - Wells, Lawrence and Dean Faulkner Wells, 1988-1996 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - White, James, 1977-1985 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Whitman, Alden, 1981-1983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Wier, Allen, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Williams, Lynna [Emory University], 1989-1990 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Winckler, Suzanne, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Wood, Jane Roberts, 1987-2005 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Correspondence about books written (author), photographs, newspaper clipping
  - Woods, Christopher, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Woolley, Bryan, 1988-1991 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Subject file about articles written (journalist), newspaper clippings
  - Wright, Lawrence, 1986-2001 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Yarborough, Ralph, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    Correspondence about article, State Senator
  - Yates, David, 1983-1985 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Zigal, Tom, 1987-1994 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Dallas Morning News, 1955-2007; 3738
  Series III is subdivided into two main subseries. The first comprises documents of Compton's early career prior to the creation of the Focus section of the Dallas Morning News. Of interest in this series are interview notes of Compton and gubernatorial candidate W. Lee O'Daniel; staff information regarding Jim Lehrer, a reporter for the Dallas Morning News from 1958-1960 and the inner-workings of the Dallas Morning News. In particular, this subseries contains information regarding the Civil Rights movements and the changes made in language with regard to African-Americans. It also illustrates how newspaper reporters made changes in how reporting was done when an African-American was the subject, especially regarding reporting of crimes.
  The second subseries within Series III, includes the years 1976 through 1998. During this time, Compton was editor of the Focus and Books sections of the Dallas Morning News. Of interest in this series are the inner-workings of the Dallas Morning News, including the shift in updated technology and use of the computer; staff information; Pulitzer Prize winners from the Dallas Morning News, author information, and press kits of notable authors, such as Tim O'Brien, Norman Mailer, Daniel Quinn, and Donley Watt. This subseries is also worthy of attention because of the information contained about the creation of the Focus section and the years dedicated getting it approved, staffed, and the new policies that were needed for the payment of book reviewers and the status of complimentary books. In addition, this series is comprised of information regarding publishing, including correspondences to and from Compton and publishers.
  - Early Career, 1955-1975; 3739
    Sub-Series Description
    This material documents Compton's news career at the Dallas Morning News prior to the creation of the Focus section of the paper. Of interest in this series are interview notes of Compton and gubernatorial candidate W. Lee O'Daniel; staff information regarding Jim Lehrer, a reporter for the Dallas Morning News from 1958-1960 and the inner-workings of the Dallas Morning News. In particular, this subseries contains information regarding the Civil Rights movements and the changes made in language with regard to African-Americans. It also illustrates how newspaper reporters made changes in how reporting was done when an African-American was the subject, especially regarding reporting of crimes.
    - Early Stories and Notes, 1956-1958; 3889 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Includes notes for stories written, including interview notes from Gubernatorial candidate W. Lee O'Daniel, Stanley Walker
    - In-House Papers, 1955-1975; 3890 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      Includes memos, desk assignments, news reporting ideas, inner newspaper workings, advertising, how to write racial identifications, complaints, office fun, staffing, newspaper clipping
    - Staff: Jim Lehrer, 1958-1960; 3891 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Story Ideas: memos, newsclippings, 3893 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Later Career, 1976-2007; 3894
    This sub-series documents the years 1976 through 2007. During this time, Compton was editor of the Focus and Books sections of the Dallas Morning News. Of interest in this series are the inner-workings of the Dallas Morning News, including the shift in updated technology and use of the computer; staff information; Pulitzer Prize winners from the Dallas Morning News, author information, and press kits of notable authors, such as Tim O'Brien, Norman Mailer, Daniel Quinn, and Donley Watt. This subseries is also worthy of attention because of the information contained about the creation of the Focus section and the years dedicated getting it approved, staffed, and the new policies that were needed for the payment of book reviewers and the status of complimentary books. In addition, this series is comprised of information regarding publishing, including correspondences to and from Compton and publishers.
    - In-House Papers, 1976-1998; 3895 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
      Includes memos, reporting assignments, inner newspaper workings, advertising and sales, complaints, office fun, staffing, newspaper clippings, photographs, retirements, Pulitzer Prize winners at Dallas Morning News
    - Staff, 3896
      - Anders, John, 1976-1977 (Box 15, Folder 5)
        Includes memos, newspaper clippings
      - Biffle, Kent, 1968-2003 (Box 15, Folder 6)
        Includes memos, letters of commendation, letters of complaint (about articles), article notes, receipts, newspaper clipping
      - Decherd, Robert, 1978-1996 (Box 15, Folder 7)
        Includes memos, correspondence
      - Hinshaw, Mike, 1980-1983 (Box 15, Folder 8)
        Includes story ideas, letters of commendation, receipts
      - Sims, Mark, 1976-1980 (Box 15, Folder 9)
        Includes memos, letters of commendation, court records, newspaper clippings, photographs
    - The Press, 1970-2004; 3902 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Includes newspaper "war" between Dallas Morning News and Dallas Times Herald, Pulitzer Prize article from Fort Worth Star-Telegram, press release regarding Dallas Morning News, articles regarding Tony Castro, remarks from Walter Cronkite (also found at Lyndon B. Johnson Library)
    - Story Ideas, 1976-1998; 3903 (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
      Includes memos, correspondences, newspaper clippings, RECAP, UT News, photographs
    - Stories, 1976-1998; 3904 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Includes completed articles, memos
    - Focus, 1976-1998
      - First Weeks, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 5)
        Includes Compton's personal notes, copies of initial issues
      - In-House Papers (1 of 2), 1976-1998 (Box 16, Folder 6)
        Includes memos, correspondences, advertising, staff assignments, letters of commendation, letters of complaint, policies, story ideas, minutes from meetings, design plates for Book Pages, newspaper clippings
      - In-House Papers (2 of 2), 1976-1998 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Focus Art, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
        Includes pen ink drawings by Bob Kolsti, Robin Tareaux
      - Stories, 1984-1991 (Box 17, Folder 3)
        Includes "A sampling – features and book notes from Book Pages," stories written by Compton, photograph
      - Book Policy, 1976-1996 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        Includes what to do with complimentary books after being reviewed, reasons for book reviewing, book sales statistics
      - Contacts - Books, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
        Includes contact information for book reviewers, publishers, authors
      - Notebook, 1996-1997 (Box 17, Folder 6)
        Includes daily notes from phone calls
      - Texas Book Themes, 1980-1998 (Box 17, Folder 7)
        Includes information about race, James Michener's Texas
      - Poetry In Motion, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 8)
        Includes information about including poetry on transportation (metro, buses)
      - Authors (National) (Box 17, Folder 9)
        Includes information about Auster, Barnes, Julian; Paul; Blout, Roy; Carver, Raymond; Crews, Harry; DeLillo, Don; Eco, Umberto; Elkin, Stanley; Gibbons, Kay; Gould, Stephen Jay; Kidder, Tracy; McInerney, Jay; McGuane, Thomas; Mailer, Norman; Mukherjec, Bharati; Price, Reynolds; Rhodes, Richard; Roth; Sheehan, Neil; Siddons, Anne River; Singer, I.B.; Stone, Robert; Woiwode, Larry; Yardley, Jonathan
      - Authors (Texas) (Box 18, Folder 1)
        Includes information, press releases, articles, and newspaper clippings about Adams, Michael; Barthelme, Donald; Bonds, Parris Afton; Bramer, Sidney; Breeder, James; Brown, Rosellen; Bryant, Dean Keith; Burke, James Lee; Carter, George; Chandra, Vikram; Condon, Richard; Cousins, Margaret; Davis, John Porterfield; Davis, Rod; DeHaloff, Henry; DeMannis, Rick; Divine, Robert; Edwards, Anne; Fairchild, Jr., H.H.; Gibson, Jewel; Griffith, Patricia, Browning; Goldbarth, Albert; Goyen, William; Greene, A.C.; Hale, Leon; Hamilton, Dagmar; Harrison, Payne; Hudgins, Andrew; Humphreys, Joel Don; Jones, Stephen Graham; Kruh, Nancy; Lea, Tom; Llwelyn, Morgan; McClellan, Tom; Maguire, Jack; Mewshaw, Michael; Morgan, D. Miller; Mullen, Harryette; Nance, Joseph Milton; Nelson, Bobby Jack; Niven, Penelope; Northcott, Kaye; Nunn, William Curtis; Oliver, Chad; Porter, Katherine Anne; Porterfield, Nolan; Powell, Padget; Quinn, Jim; Rice, Anne; Richard, Mark; Schott, Richard; Schutze, Jim; Scobie, Ingrid Winther; Solomon, Robert; Stead, Christina; Strother, Lester; Sullivan, Jim; Tippette, Giles; Turpley, Fred; Weismann, Donald; Weiss, Philip; Whitehead, Fred; Wier, Allan; Williams, Lynna; Wood, Susan; Wozencraft, Kim
    - Press Kits
      - Algonquin Books (Box 18, Folder 2)
        Includes Fall, 1990 Sampler, press kits for Kaye Gibbons, Larry Brown, photographs
      - Dallek, Robert (Box 18, Folder 3)
        Includes press kits for Lone Star Rising Lyndon B. Johnson And His Times, 1908-1960
      - Faulk, John Henry (Box 18, Folder 4)
        Includes press kit for The Uncensored, photograph
      - Glimmer Train Stories (Box 18, Folder 5)
        Includes Adams, Steven; Binham, Sallie; Byl, Christine; Engberg, Susan; Enger, Lin; Griesenner, John; McPhee, Jenny Drake; Machart, Bruce
      - Hailey, Elizabeth Forsyth (Box 18, Folder 6)
        Includes press kit for Joanna's Husband and David's Wife
      - Mailer, Norman (Box 18, Folder 7)
        Includes press kit for Oswald's Tale, two photographs
      - O'Brien, Tim (Box 18, Folder 8-9)
        Includes early galleys of In the Lake of the Woods (typed), National Author Tour – The Things They Carried
      - Quinn, Daniel (Box 18, Folder 10)
        Includes press kits for Ishmael and Providence, photograph
      - Skimm, Robert (Box 18, Folder 11)
        Includes press kits for Gray Victory, photograph
      - Watt, Donley (Box 19, Folder 1)
        Includes copies of various stories (typed)
      - Other press kits and promotional items (Box 19, Folder 2)
        Includes Stone Drug Magazine, Oxford American (John Grisham – Publisher, photograph), People, December 9, 1991 – includes article about Molly Irvins), Texas Books in Review, Current Books, Armstrong Browning Library, The Library of America (photograph), Flair
    - Press and Publishers
      - African-American Literary Review, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        Includes book reviews, news, industry trends, and issues that affect the African-American literary community
      - Book Publishers (Box 19, Folder 4)
        Includes correspondences, press releases (alphabetized), memo, photographs
      - Book Club of Texas, 1978-1994 (Box 19, Folder 5)
        Includes notes, correspondences, newspaper clippings, photocopy of Southwest Review (Spring, 1936) Item moved to backlog
      - Book Stores – Texas (Box 19, Folder 6)
        Includes correspondences, book lists, prices, book store closings, press releases (alphabetized), photographs
      - Dallas Journalism Review (Box 19, Folder 7)
        Includes Dallas Journalism Review (1973-1974), Texas Journalism Review (1975)
      - Dallas Underground Press (Box 19, Folder 8)
        Includes Dallas Observer (1980-1981), Dallas News (1971 – includes Gay Pride issue)
      - National Book Critics Circle, 1980-1986 (Box 20, Folder 1)
        Includes information about upcoming books, trends, business, correspondence
      - North Texas Skeptic, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 2)
        Includes correspondence, The Skeptic, The Comedy Wire – humor, entertainment, book reviews, and articles about pseudo-science
      - Smith College Club of Dallas, 1979-1983 (Box 20, Folder 3)
        Includes literary awards and press release, correspondence
      - Southern Methodist University, 1978-1984 (Box 20, Folder 4)
        Includes correspondences, press releases, newspaper articles, author information
      - Texas A and M Press, 1983-2007 (Box 20, Folder 5)
        Includes correspondences, press releases
      - Texas Baskerville Press, 1993-1997 (Box 20, Folder 6)
        Includes correspondences, press releases, book catalogs (book lists and pricing)
      - Texas Book Publications, 1982-1990 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        Includes correspondences, press releases, book catalogs
      - Texas Corona Press, 1981-1989 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Texas Monthly Press, 1981-1989 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Texas Publishers Association, 1981-1988 (Box 20, Folder 10)
        Includes press releases, publishers digest
      - Texas Presses, 1978-1999 (Box 20, Folder 11)
        Includes correspondences, press releases, fiction and poetry contest winners, photographs
      - Texas Pressworks, 1983-1987 (Box 21, Folder 1)
        Includes correspondences, book releases, book catalogs
      - Texas Saybrook Press, 1985-2005 (Box 21, Folder 2)
        Includes press release, funeral program, author information
      - Texas Shearer Publishing, 1982-1996 (Box 21, Folder 3)
        Includes press releases, book catalogs, copies of newspaper articles, photographs
      - Texas Southern Methodist University Press, 1982-2004 (Box 21, Folder 4)
        Includes correspondences, press releases, newspaper clippings, book jacket
      - Texas Still Point Press, 1984-1993 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - University of Texas Press, 1981-1998 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Texas Publishers Association, 1981-1985 (Box 21, Folder 7)
        Includes press releases, Publishers Digest
      - Writers News, 1990-1992 (Box 21, Folder 8)
        Includes official publication of Texas Writers Association
    - Literary Awards, 1980-2004; 3956
      - American Book Awards, 1980-1982, 3957 (Box 21, Folder 9)
        Includes lists of nominees, invitation to award ceremony
      - Governor's Sesquicentennial Conference on the Literary Arts, 1986; 3958 (Box 21, Folder 10)
        Includes program (1986), notes, spiral notebook
      - Texas Literary Hall of Fame, 2004; 3959 (Box 21, Folder 11)
        Includes program, ticket, bookmark – Friends of the Fort Worth Public Library, Inc.
      - Texas Literary Tradition, 1983-1986; 3960 (Box 21, Folder 12)
        Includes correspondences, program
    - Institutes and Societies, 1981-2006; 3961
      - Center for Texas Studies [North Texas State University], 1986-1987; 3962 (Box 21, Folder 13)
        Includes correspondences, list of charter members
      - Dallas Institute, 1982-1985; 3963 (Box 22, Folder 1)
        Includes correspondences, program ("What Makes a City," "The Economics of Taste"), report to city council, course and lecture listings
      - Eugene C. Barker Texas History Center, 1989-1995; 3964 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        Includes newsletters, The Compass Rose, Center for American History
      - Pen Texas, 1995-2006; 3965 (Box 22, Folder 3)
        Includes newsletters, invitations
      - Texas Committee on Humanities, 1983-1985; 3966 (Box 22, Folder 4)
        Includes programs, grant announcements
      - Texas Folklore Society, 1981-1985; 3967 (Box 22, Folder 5)
        Includes correspondence (see Abernethy), memos, programs
- Newspapers and Magazines, 1948-2001; 3968
  Series IV contains newspapers and magazines Compton saved from 1949 through 2001. This series contains four oversized boxes. In addition, many of the magazines and newspapers within this series are extremely fragile, and great care should be taken when handling. Of particular interest are the copies of the Dallas Morning News (1949-2001). In addition, this series contains the New York Herald Tribune (1963, 1967) that details the shift in power of the presidency to Lyndon B. Johnson after the assassination of John F. Kennedy.
  - American Journal, 1972-1973 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Includes articles, book club selections
  - AT Random, 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    Includes Random House magazine
  - The Borzoi Reader, 1989-1995 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    Includes Book excepts
  - Concho River Review, 1979-1990 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    Includes book excepts, reviews, Stone Drum, The Kenyon Review
  - Current Books, 1992-1995 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Includes book excerpts
  - The Magazine of Dallas, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    Includes culture, book excerpts, arts and entertainment
  - Doubleday Magazine for Book Lovers, 1992, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    Includes book excerpts and descriptions
  - The Oxford American, 1992-1995 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    Includes book excerpts, poetry, Southern music issue
  - Texas Books in Review [Tarleton State University], 1982-1994 (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
    Includes articles and reviews of books
  - The Texas Humanist, 1978-1982 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Includes articles and reviews
  - The Texas Observer, 1974-1985 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Includes articles, editors include Kaye Northcott and Molly Ivins
  - Single Issue Magazines (Box 24, Folder 3)
    Includes Atlantic Monthly (1975), Balcones (1987), Works in Progress (1991), Four Winds (1982), Poets and Writers (1995), Reckon (1995), Smithsonian (1980), Vanity Fair (1982)
  - Oversized – Newspapers and Magazines, 3981
    - Dallas Morning News, 1949-2001; 3982 (Box 25)
      Includes typed notes from Compton, Arts and Entertainment (1984), Book Pages (1949-1976), Book Pages – Annual Christmas Book Sections (1950-1965), Focus (1983-1984), High Profile (1988-2001), Metropolitan (1986, 1988), Sunday Reader (1996, 1998, 1999), Texas and Southwest (1993, 1998)
    - Dallas Morning News Mounted "Books" Pages and "Focus" Pages, 3983 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Includes mounted pages from the pre-run newspaper
    - Dallas Morning News – 25 Years Later, 3984 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Includes newspaper article about John F. Kennedy's assassination, 25 years later
    - Southwest Klansman, 3985 (Box 26, Folder 3)
      Includes Volume 1, Number 1, published in Dallas, Texas
    - Vortex, 1986-1988; 3986 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      Includes critical reviews
    - Single Issue Magazines, 3987 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      Includes Bright Leaf (1997), Grove Atlantic New Fiction (1995)
    - Bookletter, 1975, 1977; 3988 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      Very fragile, published by Harpers Magazine
    - The Texas Humanist, 1983-1985; 3989 (Box 27, Folder 2)
      A review of idea, history, culture
    - Lone Star Book Review, 1979-1981; 3990 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1963, 1967; 3991 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Very fragile, includes typed notes from Compton, and information about John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson
    - Single Newspapers and Magazines, 3992 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      Very fragile, includes New York Times Book Review (1992), Westward (1985), Rolling Stone (1973), Holiday (1948)